We extend a warm welcome to all.
皆さんを温かく歓迎します
Today’s session will begin
with a music-video presentation
今日の午前のプログラムも
ミュージックビデオで始まります
that will remind us of the many blessings
in store for Jehovah’s servants
エホバに仕える人たちが味わう
たくさんの祝福を思い出し
and motivate us to share
these precious truths with others.
貴重な真理を伝えたいという気持ちが
強まるでしょう
Please enjoy.
お楽しみください
これから楽しむことができるのは
During this session and the next,
we will enjoy the talks and videos
お手元のプログラムの2日目の所にある
under the Saturday heading on your program.
話とビデオです
The scripture theme for these two sessions
2日目の主題は
ペテロ第二 3:14から取られている
is taken from 2 Peter 3:14,
where we are admonished
「汚点も傷もない平和な人と
“to be found . . . spotless
and unblemished and in peace.”
神に認めていただ［く］」という
ものです
These sessions will highlight
他の人と「平和な関係を築［く］」ため
what we can individually do
to ‘pursue peace with others.’
一人一人に何ができるかを学びます
To begin,
please join in singing song number 58,
では ご一緒に58番の歌を
歌いましょう
“Searching for Friends of Peace.”
「平和を望む人を探す」
That’s song number 58.
58番の歌です
エホバに仕える私たちは
As Jehovah’s people,
we are proud to witness
about “the God of peace”
「平和の神」とその王国について
伝えることをうれしく思います
and to proclaim his Kingdom.
How can we give an effective witness
どうすれば上手に伝道し
関心を持つ人の進歩を助けられますか
and help interested ones to progress?
今日の最初のシンポジウムで
Our first symposium for this session
will address these questions.
その点が学べます
Brother Kenneth Flodin,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
教育委員会の援助者
ケニス･フローディン兄弟が
will deliver the first talk of the symposium,
シンポジウムの最初の話をします
主題は「『平和の良い知らせを伝える』
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
—Maintain Your Zeal.”
熱意を冷まさない」です
このシンポジウムのテーマは
「平和の良い知らせを伝える」です
This symposium is
about sharing “the good news of peace.”
私たちは人々がエホバとの
平和な関係を持てるよう助けています
What a privilege it is to help humble people
find peace with Jehovah!
エフェソス 6:15によると
At Ephesians 6:15,
in describing
a Christian’s “complete suit of armor,”
クリスチャンの「武具」には
履物も含まれています
it mentions our feet.
Now, back at that time,
使徒パウロは ローマの兵士たちが
thinking of Roman soldiers,
Paul knew that often they marched
何百キロも歩くことを知っていました
for hundreds of miles on Roman highways,
帝国内のあちこちを移動していたのです
crisscrossing the empire.
それでエフェソス 6:15で
こう言っています
So at Ephesians 6:15, he said this:
“Having your feet shod in readiness
「平和の良い知らせを伝える用意として
[in readiness] to declare
the good news of peace”
［用意として］履物を履いてください」
ふさわしい時にいつでも
—yes, ready to share “the good news of peace”
「平和の良い知らせ」を伝えられるよう
用意をしておくということです
on every suitable occasion.
どのように用意できるか
In this symposium, we’ll discuss five ways
5つの点をこのシンポジウムでは
取り上げたいと思います
to remain ready to preach and teach.
まず熱意を冷まさないことが
なぜ大切かを考えましょう
We’d first like to discuss
why it’s important to maintain your zeal.
Now, as an analogy,
熱意はよく 燃える火に例えられます
zeal has often been linked to fire.
We even use the expression
—don’t we?—
「あの人は燃えるような熱意を
持っている」と言うことがあります
“He has a fiery zeal for his beliefs.”
But what does “a fiery zeal” indicate?
そうした「熱意」は
どのように表れますか
ローマ 1:14, 15を
見てみましょう
Please find Romans 1:14, 15,
and here it does not
actually use the word “zeal,”
「熱意」という言葉は出てきませんが
but the sense of the word is evident.
パウロの気持ちが伝わってきます
You say: “We’re on fire,”
“We’re stoked up,” “We are ready.”
熱意や情熱や熱い思いです
Did you find it?
ローマ 1:14, 15です
Romans 1:14, 15:
「私には ギリシャ人にも外国人にも
“Both to Greeks and to foreigners,
both to wise and to senseless ones,
賢い人にも無学な人にも
“I am a debtor; so I am eager
果たすべき責任があります
それで⋯⋯ぜひ良い知らせを
伝えたいのです」
“[you see, ready with fiery zeal, eager]
熱意を抱き やる気に満ちていました
to declare the good news.”
パウロは熱意に燃え 良い知らせを
ぜひ伝えたいと思っていました
Zealous evangelizers are eager to declare
the good news—they’re “on fire.”
エホバとの平和な関係を
持ってほしかったのです
They want others to find peace with Jehovah.
でも熱意が弱まってしまうことが
あるでしょうか
But is there something
that can dampen that flame,
something that could even extinguish
the eager desire
平和を願っている人を
探したいという気持ちが
弱まってしまうことがありますか
—the readiness—
to find those who
いわば火が消えてしまうことが
あるでしょうか
even unknowingly yearn for peace?
Yes,
あります どんなことが原因で
it can be difficult
to remain eager with fiery zeal
燃えるような熱意を保つことが
難しくなることがありますか
when we face such problems as
伝道しても聞いてもらえないこと
an unresponsive territory,
あざけられること
反対されることなどです
criticism, or outright opposition to the work
—and then there are
the pressures of daily life.
それに加えて
毎日のストレスもあります
Those issues can also be likened to a fire,
こうした問題もある意味で火のようです
山火事のようなものです
to destructive fires like the wildfires
アメリカでも山火事が森林に
大きなダメージを与えています
that have plagued the western part
of the United States year after year.
Those problems can threaten
our zeal and enthusiasm.
先ほど挙げたような問題も
熱意にダメージを与えることがあります
何ができるでしょうか
So, what can we do?
英語で消防士は
ファイヤーファイターと言います
Well, there’s an English expression
that originates with firefighters.
「火と戦う人」という意味です
The expression is “Fight fire with fire.”
ファイヤーファイターは 火を使って
火と戦うこともあります
In the path of a raging wildfire,
one technique is to ignite a controlled fire.
ある場所にあえて火を付けるのです
ある一帯をあらかじめ
燃やしておくことによって
That controlled fire
consumes combustible materials.
山火事がそこまで迫ってきた時
So when the wildfire advances to that point,
there’s no fuel left
and the wildfire goes out.
火をそこで食い止めることができます
火を使って 火と戦います
Fight fire with fire.
Keep your zeal for the ministry
burning brightly.
熱意という火も燃やし続ける
必要があります
テモテ第一 4:16を見てみましょう
And now please find 1 Timothy 4:16.
熱意が弱まり 火が消えかかると
If our zeal fades—the flame smolders—
we might miss out on opportunities
to help others to gain life,
神との平和な関係を持てるよう
人々を助ける機会を
逃してしまうかもしれません
a life of peace with God.
テモテ第一 4:16です
Look at 1 Timothy 4:16 with me.
「自分自身と自分の教えに
絶えず注意を払いなさい」
It says: “Pay constant attention
to yourself and to your teaching”
自分の熱意と教えに注意を払って
—you see, the flame, the temperature.
‘Pay attention to your zeal and teaching.’
火を燃やし続ける必要があります
「粘り強く行［う］なら⋯⋯
It says: “Persevere in these things,
自分自身と⋯⋯耳を傾ける
人たちを救うことになります」
“for by doing this
you will save both yourself
and those who listen to you.”
Yes, share “the good news
of peace” with zeal.
「平和の良い知らせ」を
熱意を持って伝えるのです
次のビデオに出てくる夫婦は
Now, in the following video,
note how a couple realized
自分たちの熱意が
冷めていることに気付きます
that the flame had gone out.
They still had some glowing embers left,
でも少し火が残っているので
but they now find a way to fan the coals
いわば炭火をうちわであおいで
and regain their fiery zeal.
再び火を燃え立たせます
I don’t remember when our routine service day
いつもの奉仕の日のいつもの僕たち
became so,
well,
待てよ いつからこうなったんだ？
routine.
熱意が冷めてるような気がする
Our zeal wasn’t what it used to be.
And we were finally starting to notice.
そのことに2人とも気付いた
Not everyone wants to listen.
話を聞くかどうかは相手次第だけど
We just didn’t want to be the reason.
自分たちにもすべきことがある
It didn’t take much research to find
ちょっと調べれば
良いアイデアが見つかるし
great ideas
and set a few simple goals,
何ができるかも分かるんだ
励ましてくれる友達と
一緒に働くこともできる
like working with those
who encourage us.
With Ryota and Ami, we’re always talking
良太兄弟と亜美姉妹とはよく
どうすれば心を動かせるかについて話す
about how we can reach the heart.
We got back to basics:
基本に戻ってやってみた
Be friendly,
親しみを込めて話す
listen,
よく聞く
let the conversation progress naturally,
自然な会話を心掛ける
try to share an appealing Scriptural thought,
関心のありそうなことから
聖書の言葉につなげてみる
諦めずに続ける
and keep trying.
Our zeal
熱意は誠実な人の心に届くんだ
can attract an honest person
to the truth.
この夫婦にとって
山火事のような問題は何でしたか
In the video, what wildfires, or problems,
宣教に対する熱意が
弱まっていたのはなぜでしょうか
did the couple face that sucked the oxygen
out of their ministry?
Well, of the four we mentioned earlier,
先ほど挙げた原因にも
含まれていましたが
it seems the couple’s zeal was waning
伝道しても人々があまり
聞いてくれないように思い
because of seemingly unresponsive territory.
熱意が冷めてしまっていました
And as tired as the husband looked
in that first scene,
そして最初のシーンの夫の疲れた
顔にも表れていましたが
the pressures of daily life
might have been having a toll on him.
毎日のストレスも原因だったようです
では この夫婦はどのように
So how did they come to realize
火を使って火と戦ったでしょうか
that they needed
to fight fire with fire?
2人はキッチンでどんなことを
話していましたか
Do you remember their kitchen-table talk?
The husband mused
that “not everyone wants to listen.”
夫は「話を聞くかどうかは
相手次第」だと言いました
でも こうも言いました
But then he added,
“We just didn’t want to be the reason,”
「自分たちにもすべきことがある」
you see, the reason for them not listening.
そのことに気付いたのです
They decided to fight fire with fire.
火を使って火と戦うことにしました
They reignited their own
controlled fire of zeal
熱意の火を再び燃え立たせました
to counteract the problems
they were succumbing to.
問題に取り組むことにしたのです
Well, what were some
of the techniques they used?
2人はどうしましたか
The first was to pray to Jehovah.
まずエホバに祈りました
もしかしたら夫はローマ 12:11の
言葉を使って祈ったかもしれません
Could it be that the husband borrowed
the words of Romans 12:11 in his prayer?
Yes, he may well have asked
Jehovah to help them
夫婦が「聖なる力によって
熱意に燃え」られるよう
as a couple to “be aglow with the spirit.”
お願いしたかもしれません
夫は最初はこう言っていました
Remember he said earlier,
“I don’t remember when
our routine service day
「いつもの奉仕の日のいつもの僕たち
待てよ いつからこうなったんだ？」
became so, well, routine.”
問題と戦うには 「熱意に燃え」て
いなければなりません
Fight the wildfire by, again,
becoming “aglow with the spirit.”
相手が聞いてくれないのは
Ensure that any lack of response
こちらの熱意が足りないせい
ということがないようにしましょう
is not due to our lackluster approach.
2人はほかにもどんなことをしましたか
Well, what else did you notice
they did to rekindle their zeal?
宣教への熱意を燃え立たせるために
They did some research,
looking for suggestions
聖書や出版物を調べました
to invigorate their ministry.
聖書をよく調べれば
Yes, and regular Bible study
helps us to remember
人々を弟子とする活動を
なぜ続けるべきかが分かります
why we endure in the disciple-making work.
例えば イエスの宣教について
振り返ることができます
For example, review Jesus’ attitude
toward the ministry.
使徒たちも反対の中
大胆に伝道を続けました
The apostles’ bold witnessing
despite fiery opposition
and the disposition of Paul,
Aquila and Priscilla, Stephen,
使徒パウロ アクラとプリスキラ
ステファノなどの生き方を調べれば
力をもらえます
and other Bible characters
—these can infuse us with similar zeal.
熱意が湧いてくることでしょう
Next, keep your ministry fresh.
いつも工夫することも大切です
どのようにでしょうか
Well, what does that mean?
電話伝道で留守が多いことに
気付くかもしれません
Instead of having a number
of phone calls that go unanswered,
which is similar to having no one at home
when in the door-to-door work,
家から家の伝道で留守宅が
何軒も続くのと似ています
時間を変えてみましょう
change the time of day for witnessing
家の人がいそうな時間に電話するのです
to when more people are home.
Participate in various forms of the ministry.
いろいろな方法で伝道しましょう
You know, ironically,
興味深いことですが パンデミック前は
the pandemic more or less forced some of us
家から家の伝道ばかり
していた兄弟たちも
who were staunch door-to-door Witnesses
to branch out.
今では手紙や電話で
伝道するようになりました
We tried phone witnessing and letter writing.
さまざまな方法で
伝道するようになったことは
And now we have
a variety of preaching activities,
and this can keep us
more fully engaged and enthused.
熱意を持って打ち込む
助けになっています
ビデオの夫婦はほかにどんなことも
するようにしましたか
And did you notice what the couple
in the video set as a goal?
Periodically, they decided in advance
時々 仲間と約束して
to share in the ministry
with someone specific.
一緒に伝道することにしました
And then they determined
to talk about encouraging subjects
伝道の合間にもポジティブなことを
話し合うようにしました
when in between calls,
whether in phone witnessing
家から家に行く時も
電話伝道の時もそうできます
or in the public ministry.
人々がどう応じるとしても
Jehovah values our work in the ministry
エホバは私たちの伝道を
高く評価しています
regardless of the response we receive.
ヘブライ 6:10 ご存じですか
Hebrews 6:10—are you familiar with that?
きっとご存じでしょう
Of course you are.
そこにはエホバが
あなたの再訪問の数を
It does not say
that Jehovah does not forget
the number of return visits you make.
忘れたりしないとは書かれていません
あなたの聖書レッスンの数を忘れたり
しないとも書かれていません
It does not say he does not forget
how many Bible studies you conduct.
そうではなく あなたの
「働き［つまり努力］や
No, it says he does not
“forget your work [your effort]
［神の名に対する］愛を
忘れたり」しない とあります
and the love you showed for his name.”
宣教に対する熱意は
Our zeal for the ministry demonstrates
エホバとイエスに対する
愛の深さの表れです
that we have a deep love
for Jehovah and Jesus.
If (like the couple in the video)
you detect that your
ビデオの夫婦のように いつもと同じ
代わり映えのしない伝道をしている
ことに気付いたならどうしますか
routine of service is becoming, well,
very routine, then fight fire with fire.
火を使って火と戦いましょう
熱意を燃え立たせてください
Maintain that fiery zeal.
「平和の良い知らせ」を伝える
用意をしておきましょう
Be ready to share “the good news of peace.”
執筆委員会の援助者
ロバート･シランコ兄弟が
Brother Robert Ciranko,
a helper to the Writing Committee,
will now present
the next talk of this symposium,
シンポジウムの次の話をします
主題は
「『平和の良い知らせを伝える』
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
—Prepare Well.”
よく準備する」です
もしこうだったらどう思いますか
What would you think and how would you feel
if I showed up to give this talk
私がここに現れて話し始めますが
実は何も準備していません
but had done nothing to prepare
what to say to you
—if I had not bothered
to study the outline I was given,
もらった筋書きも読んでいませんし
主題も覚えていません
could not remember the theme,
had no idea what the main points are,
要点も知りません
and would have to guess
at what scriptures to use to support them,
もちろん どの聖句を使うかも
決まっていません
and then, as I spoke,
I would ramble incoherently?
話は支離滅裂です
あなたはきっとあきれてしまうでしょう
I’d make a very bad impression.
I know how I would feel.
私自身はというと不安でおどおどして
います あなたはこう思うでしょう
I would be a nervous wreck,
and you would wonder why
I did not think enough of you
「この兄弟はどうしてちゃんと
準備してくれなかったんだろう
to put all the time and effort
that was necessary
into preparing the talk so that you could get
the most benefit from it.
これじゃ話から何も学べない
がっかりだ」
言いたいことがお分かりですか
Can you see where I’m going with this?
Could the same things be said
何を話すかを準備せずに伝道に行ったら
if you engaged in the ministry
without first preparing what to say?
同じようなことになってしまいます
If you did not review the sample
conversations that had been provided,
「ワークブック」の話し合いの
サンプルも見ていません
話の切り出し方も考えていません
could not think of how
to start a conversation,
and did not know
what scripture to share,
開く聖句も決めていません
how nervous would you be?
あなたは不安になるはずです
And what would the householder
think of you?
家の人はどう思うでしょうか
It would likely be a very short,
uncomfortable conversation.
何を言われているか分からず
すぐに断りたくなるでしょう
And the other person may not care
to have you call again.
また話を聞いてみようという
気持ちにはならないはずです
伝道に行く前に時間を取って
よく準備することは大切です
We should take some time
to prepare well before we preach.
Why?
なぜなら 伝えているのが
最高のメッセージ
Because we have the best message ever
—“the good news of peace”
to share with people—
「平和の良い知らせ」だからです
and we should do our best so that they
will want to listen to what we have to say.
相手が聞きたいという気持ちになるよう
よく準備する必要があります
イエスは弟子たちに
伝道の準備の仕方を教えました
Jesus helped his disciples
to prepare for the ministry.
ルカ 10章によると イエスは
70人の弟子たちを伝道に遣わす前に
Luke chapter 10 reports that before
sending out 70 disciples to preach,
he shared with them a pleasant way
to greet each householder,
家の人にどのように
あいさつするとよいか
神の王国についてどう話すか
he told them what to talk about
(the Kingdom of God),
and he told them how to respond
to the varied reactions
区域の人たちの反応に合わせて
どう対応したらよいかを教えました
they would get in their territory.
As a result,
because the disciples
よく準備して伝道に出掛けたので
were fully prepared for the ministry,
弟子たちは素晴らしい経験を
することができました
they enjoyed some thrilling experiences.
When we are prepared,
私たちもよく準備していれば
自信を持って話し
we are more poised and enthusiastic
and can truly enjoy the ministry.
伝道を楽しむことができます
As you watch the following video,
次のビデオをご覧ください
notice the good results of preparing well.
よく準備することの大切さが分かります
We’d made some good changes,
僕たちだいぶ変わってきた
でもまだ何か足りない
but we weren’t done.
I asked Yuri what she planned to talk about.
友里に 「今日何話すの？」って聞いた
ぱぱっと準備 いつもこんな感じ
That started the usual scramble.
話し合いのサンプル
Then we got it—the sample conversation.
ま いけるかな
That’ll do.
あちゃー
But for that to work,
I had to remember the scripture.
聖句を覚えていなかった
今日は2人とも全然駄目だった
We were both a little forgetful that morning.
Yeah, we needed to prepare better.
そっか ちゃんと準備しないと
We’d been relying on our experience
自分ではできているつもりだったけど
and not enough on Jehovah.
もっとエホバに頼らないと
いけないんだな
So first we prepared our hearts.
まず そのことを2人で考え直した
それから何を言うかを準備した
Then we prepared our minds
and found new ways
to use our preaching tools.
新しい冊子の使い方も確かめた
Even a little preparation for initial calls
ちょっと準備するだけで
最初の訪問でも
and our returns visits
再訪問でも
went a long way.
こんなに違うんだ
夫は「そっか ちゃんと
準備しないと」と言っていました
The husband said,
“Yeah, we needed to prepare better.”
Have you ever thought that
about your ministry?
皆さんはいかがですか
Like the couple in the video,
ビデオの夫婦のように
まず今の取り組み方を考え直し 準備し
we can first prepare
our heart and our mind
ツールの使い方を
確かめることができます
and then see how best to use
our preaching tools.
Our goal should be the same
as that of the apostle Paul.
私たちはパウロと同じ決意を
抱いているはずです
At 1 Corinthians 9:23,
コリント第一 9:23で
こう言っています
he wrote that he wanted
「私は良い知らせのために
全てのことを行います
to “do all things for the sake
of the good news,
良い知らせを人々に伝えるためです」
in order to share it with others.”
では 宣教の準備について
幾つか具体的に考えてみましょう
So let’s think about some specific things
that we can do to prepare well,
beginning with what we can say
on the initial call,
まず直接の訪問であれ電話であれ
whether that is done
in person or over the telephone.
最初に何を話すかということです
Each issue of the
Christian Life and Ministry—Meeting Workbook
「クリスチャンとしての生活と奉仕
集会ワークブック」には
provides us with sample conversations
that give us some helpful ideas.
役立つ話し合いのサンプルが
載せられています
もちろんアレンジしたり
違う話題を使ったりすることもできます
Of course, you may modify the samples
or use something entirely different.
例えば 前の月の話題とか
Perhaps a subject from a previous month
or a different scripture would have
wider appeal in your territory.
別の聖句の方が
区域の人に合っているかもしれません
Your opening words may be
the most important part of the presentation,
話をどう切り出すかは特に大切なので
よく考えるようにしましょう
so think it through.
If the introduction
does not arouse interest,
出だしの言葉で相手の興味を引くことが
できないと すぐに断られてしまいます
the other person may terminate
the conversation
本題に入ることができません
before we can give a witness.
We will be more effective if we
carefully prepare
あいさつの後に何と言うか
最初の1つか2つの文を
よく準備していれば
the first sentence or two that we will say
after giving a customary greeting.
話し合いがもっと続くかもしれません
例えば 「多くの人は⋯⋯について
気に掛けていますが」とか
We might say,
“Many people are concerned about . . . ”
or “I would like
to get your opinion on . . . ”
「⋯⋯についてどう思いますか」
などと言えます
or say something else.
Then pick a topic that is of local interest
それから地元で
話題になっていることを取り上げ
and ask a well-worded viewpoint question
上手に質問して相手の考えを引き出し
that would draw the person
into the conversation.
会話するようにしましょう
Now, what about preparing
for our return visits?
では どのように
再訪問の準備ができるでしょうか
That actually begins
on the initial call by leaving a question
準備は最初の訪問の時に始まります
訪問を終える前に
家の人の興味を引く質問をします
for the person to think about
until you call again.
That is how the sample initial calls
and return visits
「ワークブック」の最初の話し合いと
再訪問もそのようにつながっています
are set up in the Meeting Workbook{
By leaving a thought-provoking question
at the end of every visit,
毎回の訪問の最後に
興味をそそる質問をすることによって
we can keep the chain of conversations
going as long as possible.
次の訪問につなげ
話し合いを続けることができます
例えで考えましょう
We can illustrate it this way:
貨物列車の先頭はエンジンのある機関車
最後尾は車掌車 後は全て貨車です
Imagine a freight train
with an engine at the front,
a caboose at the rear,
and many cars in between.
What keeps all of those cars
moving together down the train track?
全ての車両が一緒に移動できるのは
なぜでしょうか
There is a device called a coupler
at the back of each train car
それぞれの車両には
後ろに連結器が付いていて
that latches onto the coupler
at the front of the car behind it.
次の車両の前の連結器と
つながっています
By being coupled, or linked, together,
各車両がしっかりつながっているので
全ての車両は線路の上を一緒に動けます
the cars all run as a unit along the track.
So the question that we leave
with a householder at the end of one visit
毎回の訪問の最後に家の人にする質問は
連結器のような働きをします
is what we can latch onto at the beginning
of our next visit
次の訪問の始めに
その点を取り上げることができます
so that we can keep the train of thought
going from one conversation to the next.
そのようにして訪問が続いていきます
For example, on the initial call
you could ask,
例えば 最初の訪問でこう尋ねます
「つらい出来事が多いのは
なぜだと思いますか」
“Why is there so much suffering
in the world?”
After discussing that, raise the question,
その点を話し合った後 質問します
“How does God feel about our suffering?”
「神様はどう感じていると思いますか」
But don’t answer the question
until your next visit.
でもその答えは出さないでおきます
After answering that question
on the first return visit,
答えるのは次の訪問の時です
そして訪問の最後にこう尋ねます
leave the person with this question,
“What will God do to end our suffering?”
「神様は何かしてくれると思いますか」
次の訪問でその点を話し合います
This will be discussed on your next visit.
It is also important to have an objective
in mind for each return visit.
毎回の訪問の際
目的意識を持つことは大切です
Before making the call,
訪問の前に 何をしたいかを
はっきりさせておきましょう
think about what you want to accomplish
on that call.
If you raised a question the last time,
前回の訪問の最後に何か質問したなら
you’re objective will surely include
answering that question from the Bible.
今回は聖書から
答えるようにしてください
もちろん 目指しているのは
「いつまでも幸せに暮らせます」で
Of course,
the ultimate objective is to try to start
a Bible study
in the Enjoy Life Forever!{
聖書レッスンを始めることです
では 聖書レッスンの準備は
どのように行えるでしょうか
Now, what about preparing
for the Bible studies that we conduct?
Even if we know the material very well,
テキストの内容は知っていても
毎回よく準備しましょう
we should prepare for each study session
with our student in mind.
学んでいる人について考えます
That means thinking about and anticipating
その人はどんな考え方を
しているでしょうか
the views and needs of that individual.
どんなことを必要としているでしょうか
どんな点を理解しにくい
受け入れにくいと感じるでしょうか
What points might he struggle
to understand or accept?
It also means getting familiar
with the lesson
「いつまでも幸せに暮らせます」の
特長を生かしたレッスンができるよう
to be covered
in our interactive Bible course.
準備しましょう
Read the lesson carefully,
本文をよく読み 読む聖句について
どう話し合えるかを考え
look up the “read” scriptures
to see how they apply,
watch the videos that will be shown
during the lesson,
レッスンの間に使うビデオを見ましょう
and review the items
in the “Explore” section
また「見てみよう」の中にある
記事やビデオを見返し
so that you will know which of those
will be especially helpful to your student.
相手にとってどれが役立つかを
考えてください
Then you will be well-prepared
to conduct the study.
ここまでしておけば
準備万端と言えるでしょう
エホバに頼ることも大切です
Since it is ‘God who makes
the seed of truth grow’ in a person’s heart,
人の心に植えられた真理の種は
エホバが「成長させ」てくださいます
we should ask for Jehovah’s blessing
on our preparation for the study
ですからエホバの助けを求めながら
レッスンの準備をしましょう
so that we can best help
the student spiritually.
And we will be more effective
in our ministry
jw.orgと
JW Library®の特色や
if we stay up-to-date
with the latest material
最新情報に通じておくことも
宣教を上手に行う上で役立ちます
and features found
on jw.org and on JW Library®.
So learn how to navigate the website
and the app.
こうしたツールを
使いこなせるようにしておきましょう
jw.orgの「聖書の教え」の
所にある「聖書 Q&A」や
Two very helpful features on the website
are “Bible Questions Answered”
under the Bible Teachings tab
「エホバの証人について」の所にある
and “Frequently Asked Questions”
under the About Us tab.
「よくある質問」などは
とても役立ちます
JW Libraryの
「シリーズ記事」にも
They can also be found
on the app under “Article Series.”
同じ情報があります
コリント第一 3:10で
パウロは自分を
The apostle Paul described himself
at 1 Corinthians 3:10
「熟練した建築責任者」と呼んでいます
“as a skilled master builder.”
That is because he was engaging
パウロは人々をキリストの弟子にする
ために いわば建築作業をしていました
in a spiritual construction work
to build Christian disciples.
And we are doing the same sort of work
when we engage in the ministry.
私たちも宣教という
建築作業をしています
上手に建てるにはツールの使い方を
覚えなければなりません
But to build effectively,
we must learn to use our tools well.
特に主なツールである神の言葉 聖書と
We especially need to develop skill
in using our principal tool, God’s Word,
as well as learn how to make effective use
of the publications
宣教ツールボックスにある出版物を
上手に使えるようになる必要があります
in our Teaching Toolbox.
A builder who prepares
before starting to work
建物を建てる前によく準備しておけば
失敗を避け スムーズに作業できます
avoids mistakes and frustration.
Remember what the brother said
at the end of the video?
ビデオの兄弟はこう言っていました
‘Even a little preparation goes a long way.’
「ちょっと準備するだけで⋯⋯
こんなに違うんだ」
And that is what will help you
to do your best in the ministry.
準備は大切です
奉仕がもっと楽しくなります
Just as Paul recommended
at 2 Timothy 2:15
パウロはテモテ第二 2:15で
こう勧めています
—please follow along in your Bible,
if you will—
よろしければ
ご一緒に読んでみましょう
it’s 2 Timothy 2:15:
テモテ第二 2:15
「自分を神に差し出して 良いと
認められるように力を尽くしなさい
“Do your utmost to present
yourself approved to God,
真理の言葉を正しく用いることができ
“a workman with nothing to be ashamed of,
handling the word of the truth aright.”
恥じることが何もない
働き手になるのです」
Then you will experience great joy
in the spiritual building work
このように努力すれば
宣教という建築作業を十分に楽しめます
that is taking place now
because you will be ready
では 「平和の良い知らせ」を
伝えるためによく準備しましょう
and well-prepared to share
“the good news of peace.”
統治体のアンソニー･モリス兄弟が
Brother Anthony Morris,
a member of the Governing Body,
シンポジウムの次の話を
してくださいます
will now present the next talk
of the symposium,
主題は 「『平和の良い知らせを
伝える』 自分から話し掛ける」
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
—Take the Initiative.”
「平和の良い知らせを伝える」という
シンポジウムのこの話では
For this part of the symposium,
“Share ‘the Good News of Peace,’”
we’re going to discuss
the need to take the initiative.
自分から話し掛けることに
ついて考えます
Now, we’re going to look
私たちが自分から
話し掛けるべきなのはなぜか
at why we should take the initiative,
how to take the initiative,
どのように話し掛けるか
and then a concluding thought
about who’s helping
そして最後に 私たちの伝道を
誰が助けてくれているかを取り上げます
in directing us in our preaching work.
Now, first of all, why take the initiative?
まず 自分から話し掛けるべきなのは
なぜかを考えましょう
Well, think about it.
どうぞ 考えてみてください
One thing about being Jehovah’s Witnesses
私たちは24時間エホバの証人です
is that we’re never off duty.
非番はありません
We never stop being
one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
今はオフ ということはないのです
どこにいる時も 何をしている時もです
—wherever we are or whatever we’re doing.
会衆の兄弟姉妹と一緒に
So it isn’t just when we’re out
in the formal preaching work
with a congregation group
家から家の伝道などを
している時だけではありません
—we are one of Jehovah’s Witnesses
all the time.
私たちはいつでもエホバの証人です
There’s no such thing as being off duty
エホバの証人である私たちに
when we’re one of Jehovah’s Witnesses.
非番はないのです
Now, to give you an idea of how
さまざまな機会に伝道することは
なぜ大切でしょうか
significant this is
with informal witnessing,
興味深い統計をご紹介します
I will tell you a statistic:
A survey was taken some years ago
しばらく前に行われた調査の結果です
(and you’d be surprised, possibly),
きっと驚くと思います
and one group
of over 200 baptized Witnesses,
200人の兄弟姉妹を対象に
調査したところ
何と80人以上が会衆の取り決めた
伝道以外の機会に
now notice, over 40 percent
had been contacted by informal witnessing.
聖書の真理を知ったそうです
すごいですね
Isn’t that amazing?
So the door-to-door work is crucial.
もちろん 家から家の伝道は
欠かせません
Of course, during COVID-19
that’s been inhibited
ただパンデミック中は
家から家に行けないので
—letter writing has its place
and also phone witnessing.
手紙や電話で伝道しています
But the point is, there are other times
いずれにしても さまざまな機会を
捉えて伝道することが大切です
when we can do some witnessing informally.
Now, let’s examine how to do it?
では どのように行えるでしょうか
And the best example
of how to do informal witnessing
この点で最高の手本を示したのは
is, of course, Christ Jesus.
イエス･キリストです
And there’s an account that all of us
are familiar with in the Bible book of John.
皆さんもよくご存じの例が
「ヨハネによる福音書」の4章に
書かれています
So please find John chapter 4,
開いてみましょう
and we’re going to take a look
at how Jesus took the initiative
イエスがどのように
自分から話し掛けたかに注目し
and then imitate him
その手本にどう倣えるかを考えましょう
—do just as he did.
イエスはどうしたでしょうか
4章の最初の方にある通り
Now notice here in John chapter 4
(we get the context),
they’ve been traveling through Samaria.
イエスと弟子たちは旅の途中で
サマリアまで来ていました
And then verse 6, we’ll read:
そして6節にはこうあります
“In fact, Jacob’s well was there.
「ヤコブの井戸がそこにあった
“Now Jesus, tired out as he was
from the journey,
イエスは 旅のためにすっかり疲れて
井戸の所に座っていた
“was sitting at the well.
It was about the sixth hour.”
昼の12時ごろだった」
Now, that’s interesting, is it not?
興味深いと思いませんか
Jesus was tired.
イエスは疲れていました
完全でしたが 人間です
He was a perfect man, but human,
and his journey tired him out.
旅ですっかり疲れていたのです
And he’s there
about noon sitting at the well.
昼の12時ごろ
井戸の所に座っていました
どうなりましたか
And now notice what happens in verse 7:
7節です
“A woman of Samaria came to draw water.
「サマリアの女性が水をくみに来た
Jesus said to her: ‘Give me a drink.’”
イエスは 『水を飲ませて
ください』と言った」
シンプルです
「水を飲ませてください」
Real simple—“Give me a drink.”
Well, what do we learn from this?
何を学べますか
As you noticed, Jesus was tired.
イエスは疲れていました
We get tired
私たちも疲れます
because of being imperfect.
私たちは不完全だからです
If a perfect man gets tired out,
certainly we get tired.
完全な人でさえ
疲れるのですから当然です
Sometimes you may feel:
‘Well, you know, maybe I could witness
こう思うことがあるかもしれません
「この人に話し掛けたら
伝道できそうだけど
‘to this person
—take the initiative.
疲れているから今は無理」
But I just don’t feel like it.
I’m tired.’
Not with Jesus.
イエスは違いました
ですからイエスに倣いたいなら
See, to imitate Jesus,
even in the case when you’re tired,
たとえ疲れていても人を助けます
you’re thinking of others.
You want to take the opportunity
to start a conversation.
機会を捉えて話を切り出します
これが最初のステップです
That’s the initial goal.
ヨハネ 4:9からも
大切な点を学べます
Now, notice something else here
that we learn in the 9th verse
of John chapter 4:
こうあります
“So the Samaritan woman said to him:
「サマリア人女性は言った
“‘How is it that you, despite being a Jew,
『どうして水を飲ませてほしいと
言うのですか
あなたはユダヤ人で
私はサマリア人の女ですよ』」
ask me for a drink even though
I am a Samaritan woman?’”
And then we learn more here in parentheses:
そして括弧内にはこうあります
「（ユダヤ人はサマリア人と
関わりを持たないのである）」
“For Jews have no dealings
with the Samaritans.”
And it went both ways.
お互いにそうでした
偏見があったので
「関わりを持たな」かったのです
That’s the way prejudice was
—“no dealings”—
その上 相手は女性です
and on top of that, she’s a woman.
And women were not treated very nicely
当時多くの男性は
女性に敬意を持って
接していませんでした
during that period in man’s history.
でもイエスはサマリア人の
しかも女性に
So she’s a Samaritan, she’s a woman,
and Jesus asks her for a drink.
「水を飲ませてください」と言って
会話を始めました
He starts a conversation with her.
それで こういう点を学べます
Now, these are the things we learn from this:
He didn’t make any assumptions about her
イエスは偏見を持っていませんでした
相手が女性であるということは
見れば分かりますし
and obviously knew that she was a woman
and a Samaritan traveling
through Samaria at that time.
サマリアで出会ったので
サマリア人であることも分かります
And he didn’t refuse
to speak to her
それでもイエスはその女性に
話し掛けました 自分の方からです
because of that.
ですから こういう点を学べます
So the lesson for us is:
Don’t judge people by what you see,
人を見掛けで判断すべきではありません
based on their culture
or color of their skin.
国や人種が違ってもです
This world is filled with judges.
世の中 決め付ける人ばかりです
We’re Jehovah’s Witnesses.
でも私たちはそうはしません
We don’t do that.
人のことを判断できるのは
エホバとイエスだけです
We leave the judging
to Jehovah and Jesus Christ.
この人は会話してくれるはずがない と
決め付けるのは間違いです
And don’t judge
whether you think they’ll converse with you.
That’s wrong.
イエスは決め付けませんでした
Jesus didn’t do that,
and he set the perfect example for us.
私たちにとって最高の手本です
話し掛けてみてください
Go ahead, and if you’re
a little nervous about it,
もし勇気が出ないなら
エホバに祈って助けを求めてください
then we beg Jehovah for his spirit to help us
エホバに 「あなたの素晴らしい名前と
お考えについて話せるよう
and to give us the courage to witness
about his beautiful name and purposes.
助けてください」と祈るのです
Now, he also teaches us
また イエスの手本から
ほかにも大切な点を学べます
something else interesting here.
And this is where in taking the initiative,
真理についていっぺんに
話さないようにする ということです
you start a conversation;
まずは話し掛けてみましょう
you don’t rush into things.
先ほど9節を読みましたが
その後の部分を見ると
Now notice, we read verse 9,
and then they had
this conversation take place
どんなやり取りが
行われたかが分かります
through these following verses here.
24節でイエスは
「神は見えない方で
We get to verse 24 where he mentions
聖なる力と真理に導かれて崇拝
しなければならない」と言っています
that ‘God is a Spirit, and you
must worship him with spirit and truth.’
And now here’s what happens
水を飲ませてください とお願いした
ことがきっかけで始まった会話が
after they had this fine conversation
and after he simply asked for a drink.
発展しています
Notice verse 25:
25節 「女性は言った
“The woman said to him:
『私は メシアが来ることを
知っています
“‘I know that Messiah is coming,
who is called Christ.
キリストと呼ばれる方です
Whenever that one comes,
he will declare all things to us openly.’”
その方が来たら 全てのことを
はっきり知らせてくださいます』」
She spoke out of her heart.
信じていることを話していますね
Now notice verse 26:
26節にはこうあります
「イエスは言った
“Jesus said to her: ‘I am he,
『あなたと話している私がそうです』」
the one speaking to you.’”
My, what a moment!
まさかの展開です
And she’s blessed
with having the Messiah himself speak to her.
女性は メシアから直接
このことを知らされたのです
However, give it some thought.
でも ちょっと考えてみてください
What if Jesus, rather than saying:
もしイエスがこのように話を切り出して
いたらどうなっていたでしょうか
“Give me a drink,”
started off with saying:
「私はメシアです
水を飲ませてください」
‘I am the Messiah.
Give me a drink.’
Hmm, I don’t know.
んー きっとうまく
いかなかったでしょう
Because Jesus had Jehovah’s spirit
and heavenly wisdom,
でもイエスはエホバに導かれ知恵を
働かせて まず会話を楽しみました
he entered the conversation first.
私たちもイエスの手本に
倣いたいと思います
So that’s what we want
to keep in mind and try to do ourselves
—to have a conversation.
会話をすることです
It might just be speaking from your heart
まずは自分の気持ちを
口にしてみましょう
and trying to engage the person.
相手は興味を持ってくれる
かもしれません
For example, you could be
in the doctor’s office waiting room.
例えば 病院の待合室にいるとします
So you speak from your heart,
隣の人と目が合ったら
自分の気持ちを口にしてみましょう
and you notice the person is looking at you:
「あーあ 病気なんて
早くなくなってしまえばいいのに」
“Boy, I look forward to the day
when I’ll never be sick again.”
Well, they could look at you and think,
まあ おかしなことを言っている と
思われるかもしれません
‘Well, this guy is crazy.’
Or they could say: “Well, that would be nice.
でも中には うなずいて
「ほんとにそうなったらいいですね」と
言う人もいるかもしれません
What makes you believe
that’s going to happen for you?”
Either way, you’re starting
相手がどう反応するかは分かりませんが
to take the initiative
to start a conversation,
とにかく話のきっかけを
つくってください
and leave the rest to Jehovah.
後はエホバにお任せしましょう
良い結果につながったら
エホバのおかげです
He’s the one
that gets the credit for the results.
Now, next, we have a video here.
では 次のビデオをご覧ください
Now, as you watch the following video,
ビデオに出てくる姉妹が
出会った人に話し掛けようとします
notice how a sister
finds an effective way
どんな方法が良いか
一緒に考えてみてください
to witness informally.
They seemed nice.
いい人たちそう
友里は話し掛けたいんだな
I knew what Yuri was thinking.
I wanted to start a conversation,
話し掛けてみたいけど
邪魔したくないし
but I didn’t want to bother them either.
今話せるかも
And when an opportunity came,
何も言えなかった
I just froze.
何か渡さなきゃ
Then I was in a rush to give a witness.
It felt forced.
なんか無理やりだったな
It helped to hear that we’d all been there.
よくあることだよって言ってくれた
Our past experiences were similar.
みんなそうだって
気負わずに 身近なことに
ついて話してみれば
Whenever we didn’t put pressure on ourselves
and just looked for something in common
to talk about,
そのうち聖書のことも話せるかも
we could usually find a moment
when we could say something about the Bible.
She was curious why we were dressed up.
「ネクタイしてお出掛けですか」って
聞かれた
It turns out that she’d never talked
エホバの証人のこと
初めて聞いたみたい
to Jehovah’s Witnesses before.
So we appreciated
how she took the initiative.
姉妹は自分の方から
話し掛けようとしました
Of course, you see the contrast there
that at one point she froze.
でも 最初は何も言えませんでした
So it is stressful—no doubt about it.
きっと緊張してしまったんでしょう
無理もないことです みんなそうです
We’re only human.
その後 姉妹は女性を追い掛けて
パンフレットを渡そうとしました
But then she rushed
into things running after her with the tract.
See, give it some thought.
もっと良い方法がありますか
Try to have a conversation,
イエスに倣って話を切り出し
then let the spirit move it,
and that would be imitating Jesus.
後は聖なる力に導いてもらうことです
Then this can move
to getting into the spiritual purpose
もしかしたら 会話が次第に発展して
真理について自然に話すことが
できるかもしれません
of initiating the conversation.
So a good example,
give it a try, brothers and sisters,
では 皆さんもやってみてください
そうすれば エホバが
助けてくれるでしょう
and let Jehovah bless your efforts.
Now, to conclude,
最後に 励みになる点を
お話ししたいと思います
I want to share this beautiful thought
自分から話し掛けて
when it comes to this work we’re engaging in
「平和の良い知らせ」を伝える
and sharing “the good news of peace”
by taking the initiative.
勇気が湧いてくるに違いありません
Never forget this, and you know it,
but it’s a good reminder
すでにご存じの点と思いますが
振り返ってみましょう
—Revelation chapter 14.
啓示 14章です
And here in Revelation
啓示 14:6です こうあります
(familiar to most of you listening),
「また私は 別の天使が
空高く飛んでいるのを見た
and verse 6, let’s read it:
“And I saw another angel flying in midheaven,
その天使は 地上に住む人々
“and he had everlasting good news to declare
すなわち あらゆる国や民族や
言語や種族の人々に伝える
“to those who dwell on the earth, to every
nation and tribe and tongue and people.”
永遠の良い知らせを携えていた」
Now, this is profound, obviously,
勇気が湧いてくるのではありませんか
ここには「天使が空高く飛んでいる」と
書かれています
an “angel flying in midheaven.”
The footnote helps us;
it’s overhead
「空高く」というのは
鳥が飛んでいる辺りのことです
—where the birds fly.
You know, you see them.
天使が私たちのすぐそばを
飛んでいるのです
See, another ‘angel in midheaven,’
that’s how close they are.
それで ぜひそのことを
じっくり考えてください
And this is something
you want to meditate on.
Personally, when I was in the traveling work,
以前 旅行する奉仕をしていた時
sometimes I’d be working with one
of the brothers or one of the sisters,
会衆の兄弟や姉妹と一緒に
伝道しましたが 場所によっては
and they had opposition
家の人にとても厳しいことを
言われることがありました
in some of the territories we’d work.
And I could tell they’re feeling the stress,
落ち込んでしまう兄弟姉妹もいました
and I know it was because of the reaction
of some of these householders.
結構きついことを言われることが
あったからです
そんな時私はよく
So, what I used to enjoy doing
(and they appreciated it
after they realized what I was doing),
兄弟姉妹にこう言って励ましました
しばらく一緒に歩いた後
立ち止まって上を見上げ こう言います
we’d be walking along
and then I would just stop and I’d look up.
And I’d say, “Do you see him?”
「あれ 誰ですか」
And they’d say, “Who?”
「えっ 何？」
“He’s right up there above the trees.”
「あの木の上の方ですよ」
すると 兄弟 頭大丈夫ですか
という顔で私を見ます
And they’d look at me like,
‘Our circuit overseer has lost it.’
But I said, “See,”
私は 「見てください」と言って
啓示 14:6について話します
and I would tell them
about Revelation 14:6.
私たちが伝道する時
When we’re in the preaching work,
whether it’s informal or formal door-to-door,
家から家でも他の場所でも
収穫を行っているのは天使たちです
the angels are the real reapers.
少なくとも1人の天使がそばにいます
At least one is nearby.
What a profound thought!
勇気が湧いてきませんか
天使たちが収穫を行っています
They are the real harvesters.
「正しい態度を持つ」人たちの所に
私たちを連れて行ってくれます
They are the ones directing us
to the “rightly disposed” people.
それを忘れないでください
Don’t ever forget that.
「平和の良い知らせ」を伝えるため
When it comes to being ready
to share “the good news of peace,”
勇気を出して
自分から話し掛けてください
you go ahead and take the initiative
to start conversations.
会話を始めるのです
You’ll have valuable opportunities
では さまざまな機会を活用して
to share “the good news of peace.”
「平和の良い知らせ」を伝えましょう
奉仕委員会の援助者
ゲーリー･ブロー兄弟が
Now, Brother Gary Breaux,
a helper to the Service Committee,
will now present the next talk
of this symposium,
シンポジウムの次の話を
してくださいます
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
主題は 「『平和の
良い知らせを伝える』
—Follow Up on Interest.”
興味を示した人を助ける」です
To encourage us to promptly follow up
良い知らせに興味を示した人を
すぐに助けることはとても大切です
on interest that we find
in the field ministry,
Paul likens our work to a plant
パウロは 宣教を種が芽を出して
成長することに例えています
that grows from a little seed.
種が芽を出して成長するには
何が必要ですか
Now, what’s vital for a planted seed to grow?
専門家はこう言っています
One authority says:
“Of all the factors
that determine seed germination,
「種の発芽には
いろいろなものが必要だが
water is the first and most important.”
一番重要なのは水である」
別の人はこう書いています
And another reference says:
“Until seeds have sprouted,
keep the seed bed moist,
「種が発芽するまで 土を湿らせ
乾かないようにすることが大切である」
never allowing it to dry out.”
So, what will happen
to a seed that is not watered?
では もし種に水をやらなければ
どうなりますか
芽は出ません 成長しないのです
Nothing!
It will lay dormant.
See, regular watering
is vital for a seed to sprout,
ですから 定期的に水をやることが
種が芽を出し 根付き
成長する上で欠かせません
to take root
and, in fact, continue to grow.
Now, with these facts in mind,
パウロも同じようなことを言っています
Paul’s words at 1 Corinthians 3:6
コリント第一 3:6で
show that more is required
真理の種をまく以上のことを
行う必要がある と教えています
than simply planting a seed of truth.
Let’s note his words.
ご一緒に読んでみましょう
コリント第一 3:6です
It’s at 1 Corinthians 3:6.
こうあります
It says:
“I planted, Apollos watered,
「私は植え アポロは水を注ぎました
しかし 成長させたのは神です」
but God kept making it grow.”
So all credit goes to Jehovah God
for making the spiritual seed grow,
種を成長させるのは神です
ですから 神が賛美されるべきです
but he allows us
to have a role in the process.
でも 私たちにもできることがあります
Did you notice
the important role Apollos played?
アポロは大切な役割を果たしました
He did the watering.
水を注ぎました
In a regular way,
興味を示した人の心に
he helped keep
the spiritual soil of the individual moist,
いわば定期的に水を注ぎました
土が乾いてしまわないように
するためです
never allowing it to dry out.
Many people who show interest
in the Kingdom message today
王国のメッセージに
興味を示す人の多くは
are searching for the truth about God.
神についての真理を知りたいと
思っています
そのような人に神について教えるには
In order to teach them progressively,
we must return again and again.
何度も訪問しなければなりません
This requires good preparation
そのためには 予定を立て
and organization on our part.
よく準備する必要があります
By promptly making return visits,
相手を深く気遣っているなら
we demonstrate
a sincere concern for the individual,
すぐに再訪問を行うよう
努力するはずです
wanting to help them grow spiritually
その人に成長してほしい
エホバとの友情を築いてほしい と
願っているからです
and develop a relationship with Jehovah.
次のビデオをご覧ください
In the following video,
notice how a sister follows up
on interest shown.
姉妹は興味を示した人を
どのように助けるでしょうか
Ami left a great question for her next visit.
亜美ちゃん 上手に再訪問につなげてる
Return visit! Mrs. Iwata!
あっ 再訪問！ 岩田さん
どうしよう 今日の午前中に行くって
言ってたんだった
I told her I’d visit this morning.
I just didn’t schedule the time.
帰る前に寄ってみよう
I could at least stop by on the way back.
I missed her again.
またお留守だった
If I didn’t try something different,
やり方を変えないと
I was just going to keep missing her.
これからもずっと会えないかも
First, I wanted her
まず来たことは伝えたい
to know I hadn’t forgotten her.
Dear Mrs. Iwata,
「岩田さんへ
I hope you’re doing well.
お元気ですか
I promise to come by early next week.
また来週初めにお寄りします
By the way, your flowers are so beautiful!
玄関のお花 きれいですね」
Then I made a plan for my service day.
そして奉仕の予定を立てた
Following through is just too important
再訪問の予定を立てるって大事なんだな
to leave to chance.
As you plan your share in the ministry,
宣教を行う際 ビデオに出てきた
姉妹の手本に倣い
follow the good example
of the sister in the video
and schedule time
to make regular return visits.
再訪問を定期的に行う時間を
取り分けましょう
Doing so is just as important
再訪問は宣教の他の面と
同じように大切です
as other aspects of our ministry.
These regular visits with interested people
良い知らせに興味を示した人を
定期的に訪問することは
are vital links in the chain
leading to a Bible study.
聖書レッスンにつなげる上で
欠かせません
In our ministry,
we often compliment the householder
私たちはよく 家の人の庭の美しい花や
植物を褒めることがあります
for the beautiful flowers or plants
in their yard,
just like the sister did in the video.
ビデオの姉妹もそうしていました
では 花が育ったのはなぜですか
But how did they get that way?
Well, the householder
probably watered them on set days
家の人は時間を決めて
水をやっていたのかもしれません
or even used an automatic sprinkler timer
あるいは スプリンクラーを使って
自動的に水がまかれるように
していたのかもしれません
to schedule regular watering cycles.
See, to have healthy and vibrant plants,
花や植物が元気に育つために
watering cannot be left to chance.
定期的な水やりは欠かせません
Well, how can we apply that to our ministry?
宣教に当てはめて考えてみましょう
Before leaving a person
that has shown interest,
興味を示す人に会ったら
立ち去る前に
endeavor to set
the proper time to water.
次にいつ訪問して水を注ぐかを
決めるようにしてください
種の成長を促すためです
The water of truth will come on.
See?
このように言えるかもしれません
Perhaps ask, “On what day or hour
would you like for me to return
「またお話するため 次はいつ
何時ごろ伺ったらいいでしょうか」
to continue our discussion
or to answer the question?”
そう尋ねることによって
相手に敬意を示せます
See, this consideration
really dignifies the person,
都合の良い日時を
家の人に決めてもらうのです
allowing them to share
in setting the appointment.
興味を示す人に会ったら
It’s important that we be willing
to water an interested person
その人にとって一番都合の良い時間に
at the most convenient time for them.
水を注ぐことが大切です
Then, just like setting a timer,
そして 約束の日時を忘れないよう
put that appointment
where you’ll remember it.
何かに記録しておきましょう
The sister in the video
put it in her electronic calendar
ビデオの姉妹は 次に訪問する日時を
so she could be reminded later.
スマホの予定表に入れておきました
再び訪問することを約束したなら
If you promise someone that you’ll return,
then keep your promise.
約束を守りましょう
イエスがマタイ 5:37で
言ったことを
Remember Jesus’ simple statement
recorded at Matthew 5:37:
覚えておられると思います
“Just let your word ‘Yes’ mean yes.”
「『はい』は はいを⋯⋯
意味するようにしなさい」
If they’re truly interested,
本当に聖書のことを知りたい人なら
約束の時間に家にいるように
してくれるかもしれません
they may go to great efforts
to keep the appointment.
How disappointed they would be
if we didn’t show up!
待っていたのに伝道者が来なかったら
がっかりすることでしょう
Following through is just too important
約束した時間を守ることは
とても大切です
to leave to chance.
必ず守りましょう
Because of the busy lives
that people have today,
人々は忙しい生活を送っています
ですから 再訪問してもなかなか
家の人に会えないかもしれません
it may be hard
to find the person at home again,
even if you set an appointment.
約束していてもです
ですから 相手の電話番号など
So it’s a good idea to try
and obtain his contact information,
連絡先を教えてもらえないか
聞いてみるのは良いことです
maybe his phone number.
Some publishers anticipate this challenge
家の人にこう尋ねるようにしている
兄弟姉妹もいます
and simply ask, “Do you text?”
「メールはしますか」
By simply texting,
メールをすることができるなら
you may be able to keep in touch
and cultivate the interest further.
連絡を取り合ってさらに興味を
持ってもらうことができるでしょう
And if you can’t get his contact information
もし連絡先が分からず
約束した時間に行っても
家の人がいないなら
and the person isn’t home
at the agreed-upon time,
簡単なメモを残すことができます
you might leave a brief note,
just as the sister did in the video.
ビデオの姉妹もそうしていましたね
そうするなら 家の人は 覚えてくれて
いたんだと感じることでしょう
And this will assure the householder
that you haven’t forgotten them.
人々を弟子とするには
粘り強さや諦めないことが大切です
The disciple-making work
requires patience and persistence.
伝道の書 11:6の言葉を
思い出します
In this regard, note what
Ecclesiastes 11:6 says.
読んでみましょう
Ecclesiastes 11:6
—it says:
伝道の書 11:6
“Sow your seed in the morning
「朝に種をまき 夕方になるまで
手を休めてはならない
“and do not let your hand rest
until the evening;
“for you do not know
which will have success,
あなたは どの種が育つか
“whether this one or that one,
これかそれか あるいは
両方なのかを知らないからだ」
or whether they will both do well.”
When it comes to planting literal seed,
文字通りの種まきの場合
we don’t know when and where it will sprout.
種がいつ どこで芽を出すか
分かりません
私たちにコントロールできない
たくさんの要素が関係しています
Many factors are beyond our control.
これは人々を弟子とする活動にも
当てはまります
Something similar can be said
of the disciple-making work.
We need to be patient and positive
大事なのは粘り強さと諦めないことです
because we don’t know who will respond.
誰が真理を受け入れるか
分からないからです
Last and of utmost importance:
最後に とても大切な点があります
Even if the return visit is brief,
短い再訪問であっても
聖書から 役立つ点を
伝えるようにすることです
share a Scriptural thought.
The spiritual content of our conversation
聖書から役立つ点を話すなら
家の人は他の訪問からは得られない
爽やかさを感じるでしょう
is what makes our visit different
from any others that they may have.
近所の人や友達や同僚や親族も
その家に来ることがあるでしょう
See, they have neighbors,
friends, workmates,
or relatives that check in on them.
でも 家の人が神を知るようになるには
But for them to grow spiritually,
the water of truth from God’s Word
must be dispensed.
神の言葉から真理の水を
注がなければなりません
See, conveying
just a brief Scriptural thought
再訪問のたびに 短くても
役立つ点を聖書から伝えるなら
may provide just enough
家の人の心という土が
乾くことはないでしょう
to keep their spiritual soil moist.
興味を示した人を再訪問することは
The work involved of following up interest
is a very important assignment
エホバが私たち一人一人に与えている
大切な割り当てです
that Jehovah has given to each of us.
With this in mind,
let’s return to Paul’s illustration
パウロの例えにもう一度注目し
エホバが私たちを
どう見ているかを考えましょう
and see how Jehovah views us.
It’s back at 1 Corinthians chapter 3,
コリント第一 3:9をご覧ください
and verse 9.
It says:
「私たちは神と共に働く者だからです
“For we are God’s fellow workers.
皆さんは 神が耕している畑
You are God’s field under cultivation,
God’s building.”
神の建物です」
It’s an honor to be one
of “God’s fellow workers.”
「神と共に働」けるのは光栄なことです
神と共に働くことで
神と隣人への愛を示せます
It enables us to show our love
for him and for our neighbors.
It brings us great joy
to share “the good news of peace”
興味を示した人を助け
「平和の良い知らせ」を伝えるなら
by following up on interest shown.
大きな喜びを味わえます
And we can be assured
that those who respond favorably
興味を示した人をすぐに助けるために
一生懸命努力し その人が
エホバを崇拝するようになるなら
will forever appreciate our diligent efforts
when they recall how we promptly followed up
その人はあなたの努力に感謝し
ずっと忘れないことでしょう
when they showed interest.
Brother William Malenfant,
a helper to the Teaching Committee,
教育委員会の援助者
ウィリアム･マレンフォント兄弟が
will now present
the final talk of this symposium,
シンポジウムの最後の話をします
主題は 「『平和の
良い知らせを伝える』
“Be Ready to Share ‘the Good News of Peace’
学んでいる人の成長を助ける」です
—Help Students Grow to Maturity.”
Basic Bible teachings are wonderful.
聖書の基本的な教えは
素晴らしいものです
Usually,
it’s the fundamental doctrines of the Bible
多くの人は聖書の基本的な教え
基礎的な教えを聞いて
—basic teachings—
that draw people to the truth.
真理に引き寄せられます
However, learning basic Bible teachings
でも 聖書のそのような教えを
学ぶだけでは
is just the beginning
of knowledge about Jehovah.
エホバについて十分
知ることはできません
At Hebrews 6:1,
ヘブライ 6:1で使徒パウロは
the apostle Paul exhorts
all students of God’s Word
聖書を学んでいる人全てが
さらに先に進む必要がある
と教えています
to progress beyond basic teachings.
ヘブライ 6:1を読んでみましょう
This is what is stated at Hebrews 6:1:
“Therefore, now that we have moved beyond
「それで 私たちはキリストに関する
初歩の教理より先に進んだのですから
“the primary doctrine about the Christ,
十分に成長するように努力しましょう」
let us press on to maturity.”
Isn’t that what we want to achieve
with our Bible students,
聖書を学んでいる人にも
そうなってほしいと思います
初歩の教理より先に進んで
to help them move beyond the primary doctrine
十分に成長してほしいと願っています
and progress to Christian maturity?
It comes about in degrees
学んでいる人が成長するには
as students acquire
an increased level of knowledge
聖書の知識を学び
真理に対する愛を強めて
いかなければなりません
and appreciation for the truth.
Bible students must learn to love God
神と神の基準を愛するように
なる必要があります
and his standards and appreciate
また 神が行うことや
私たちに求めることは全て
that all of his ways and requirements
愛に基づいているということを
理解する必要もあります
are expressions of his love for us.
When Bible students experience the good
学んでいる人自身がエホバに従い
that comes from obeying Jehovah
倣うことによって良い結果を経験すると
and following his ways,
their love for him will deepen.
エホバをもっと愛するようになります
As you watch the following video,
次のビデオをご覧ください
please note how a sister helps her student
聖書を学んでいる人が成長できるよう
姉妹はどのように助けるでしょうか
to make progress toward maturity.
岩田さん よく頑張ってる
Mrs. Iwata was doing great.
We were already on Lesson 10.
もうレッスン10まで来た
集会にも早く来てくれたらいいな
I really hoped she’d come to a meeting soon.
ヘブライ 10:24, 25を考えて
We talked about Hebrews 10:24, 25
and watched the video.
ビデオも見た
あれ 私 何かやっちゃった？
Did I miss something?
あ そっか
I guess I did.
レッスンを進めていくこと
ばっかり考えてた
I was too focused
on our progress with the lessons
instead of her progress and what she needed.
岩田さんの気持ち 考えてなかった
ご主人に 集会に行くなと
言われたみたい
Mr. Iwata said going to meetings
would dishonor the family.
He wanted her to quit the study.
レッスンもやめてほしいって
She didn’t want to quit,
岩田さんはやめたくないけど
but whenever she tried to talk about it,
they argued.
話そうとすると
言い合いになっちゃうって
We showed her where to look for help
役立ちそうな記事を見せて
and made time during our studies
それについて一緒に話し合った
to talk about it more.
And we all prayed for Jehovah
努力が実りますように と
みんなエホバに祈った
to bless her efforts.
We did our best
to share the good news of peace,
平和の良い知らせを伝えるために
ベストを尽くした
エホバは祈りを聞いてくれた
and Jehovah did the rest.
ビデオの女性は 集会に出席し
As we saw, the student took an important step
toward Christian maturity
十分に成長するための
大切な一歩を踏み出しました
when she began to attend meetings.
As you study with your student
「いつまでも幸せに暮らせます」の
レッスン7から11では
lessons 7 to 11
of the Enjoy Life Forever!{
どんなことを強調できるでしょうか
please be sure to highlight
それらのレッスンで取り上げられている
Jehovah’s appealing qualities
エホバの魅力的な性格に
注意を向けるようにしてください
that are set forth in those lessons.
For example, lesson 7
of the Enjoy Life Forever! {
例えば レッスン7では
エホバの愛がどれほど素晴らしいかを
学ぶことができます
describes Jehovah’s loving ways.
We want to help our students to understand
一緒に聖書を学んでいる人が
that Jehovah
really does love them as individuals
エホバは本当に自分を愛してくれている
永遠に生きてほしいと願っている
と感じられるよう助けてください
and wants them to achieve everlasting life.
The apostle John highlights Jehovah’s love
ヨハネ第一 4:9には エホバの
愛について書かれています
at 1 John 4:9
ヨハネは エホバが
イエスを地球に遣わし
by pointing out
that Jehovah sent Jesus to earth
to take our place in death
私たち自身の罪や
アダムから受け継いだ罪が
and thus pay for our inherited sins
許されるようにしてくださった
ことを書いています
and our personal sins.
Yes, out of love,
エホバは愛に動かされて
Jehovah provided a way for us
私たちがご自分に気兼ねなく
近づけるようにしてくださいました
to enjoy an approved standing with him.
エホバは本当に愛情深い方です
This is one of Jehovah’s loving ways.
レッスン8は エホバとの友情を
取り上げています
Lesson 8 shows us
how to become Jehovah’s friend.
This is likely something that most people
have never even thought of.
多くの人は神と友達になれるなんて
考えたこともないでしょう
Can you imagine the privilege
このレッスンでは どうすればエホバの
友達になれるかを学びます
of becoming God’s friend?
Help your students to see how their obedience
学んでいる人にぜひ理解してほしいのは
エホバとの友情を育てるには
and exclusive devotion to Jehovah
エホバに心から従う必要が
ある ということです
pave the way to friendship with him.
Proverbs 3:5, 6
格言 3:5, 6には
tells us specifically
エホバが何を望んでいるかが
具体的に書かれています
what Jehovah wants us to do.
Proverbs 3:5, 6 says:
格言 3:5, 6です
“Trust in Jehovah
「心を尽くしてエホバに頼れ
“with all your heart,
“and do not rely on your own understanding.
自分の考えに頼ってはならない
どんな道を行く時にも神のことを考えよ
“In all your ways take notice of him,
そうすれば神が真っすぐに
進ませてくださる」
and he will make your paths straight.”
We show our trust in Jehovah
エホバを心から信頼し
by doing what he tells us to do
エホバの言う通りにするなら
and thereby become his friends.
エホバの友達になることができます
Jehovah takes good care of his friends,
エホバは友達を大切にし
and he is always loyal to them.
揺るぎない愛を示してくださいます
Lesson 9 highlights the power of prayer.
レッスン9では
祈りの大切さを学びます
Teach your Bible students
学んでいる人に エホバにどのように
祈れるかを教えてください
how to pray to Jehovah.
In addition to prayer,
神との友情を育てるには 祈りに加えて
regular Bible reading is also necessary
聖書を定期的に読むことも欠かせません
to make spiritual progress.
Psalm, the first Psalm,
詩編 1:2, 3は
verses 2 and 3, encourages Bible reading.
そのことを勧めています
ご一緒に読んでみましょう
Let’s look it up together.
That’s Psalm, the first Psalm,
詩編 1編2節と3節を
読んでみましょう
and we’re going to read verses 2 and 3.
It’s speaking about a man of God
神の言葉を喜ぶ人のことが
書かれています
who takes delight in God’s Word.
こうあります
It says: “But his delight
「その人はエホバの律法を喜び
“is in the law of Jehovah,
［聖書に書かれている律法のことです
続いてこうあります］
“[well, the law of Jehovah
is found in the Bible,
“and it says,] and he reads His law
昼も夜も小声で読む
“in an undertone day and night.
“He will be like a tree planted
by streams of water,
水の流れのほとりに
植えられた木のようになり
“a tree that produces fruit in its season,
時期が来ると実を結び
“the foliage of which does not wither.
その葉は枯れない
And everything he does will succeed.”
行うことは全て成功する」
つまり神の基準に従うなら
Yes, “everything he does” as a Christian,
行うことは全て成功するのです
leading a Christian life, “will succeed.”
Reading God’s Word
聖書を読んで当てはめるなら
and then putting it into practice
brings Jehovah’s blessing.
エホバは祝福してくださいます
一緒に聖書を学んでいる人が
Now, if you have a student
教育を十分に受けられなかった
といった理由で
who feels limited in his learning ability,
perhaps because of a lack of education,
勉強に苦手意識を持っているなら
please encourage him
to go to Jehovah in prayer
ぜひエホバに祈って助けを
求めるよう勧めてください
and persist in asking him
「あなたの言葉を
理解させてください」と
粘り強く祈るよう励ましましょう
for help to understand his Word.
James 1:5
ヤコブ 1:5にある通り
assures us that Jehovah is ready and willing
エホバはご自分に「求め続け」る人を
いつでも喜んで助けたいと
思っているのです
to help those
who ‘keep on asking’ him for help.
Lesson 10 gives this direction:
レッスン10で勧められているのは
As soon as possible,
集会に出席するよう
invite Bible students
to attend congregation meetings.
できるだけ早く誘うことです
What your student hears and observes
at Christian meetings
学んでいる人は 集会で
見たり聞いたりすることに
感動するかもしれません
can touch his heart
and will help him to progress.
エホバとの友情が深まることでしょう
So when you show your student the video
それで 「王国会館においでください」
の動画を一緒に見る時
What Happens at a Kingdom Hall?,
that would be a good time
to warmly invite him
集会に来て実際の様子を
見るよう誘ってみましょう
to attend meetings.
Also, be sure to invite
a variety of publishers
また いろいろな背景を持つ兄弟姉妹に
レッスンに参加してもらってください
to accompany you on the study.
In that way, your student will get acquainted
そうすれば 学んでいる人は
兄弟姉妹と知り合い
with others in the congregation,
and he will likely feel more at home
when he attends our meetings.
集会に来た時にリラックスして
楽しむことができるでしょう
レッスン11では 学んでいる人に
Lesson 11: In this lesson,
we are encouraged to teach our students
聖書の調べ方を教えるよう
勧められています
how to do personal study
jw.orgやJW Library®の
使い方を教えることができます
using jw.org and JW Library{
Show your student how to use these tools.
これらのツールの使い方を
教えてあげてください
If you feel a bit unsure
about teaching someone
電子機器が苦手で上手に
説明する自信がない場合は
to make use
of their electronic device for research,
どうしたらいいでしょうか
don’t hesitate to ask
for help from the congregation.
会衆の兄弟姉妹に
遠慮なく助けてもらってください
There are many
who would be delighted to assist you.
喜んで助けてくれる人が
たくさんいるはずです
The blessings that we receive
when we teach someone the truth
誰かに真理を教えることによって
味わえる喜びについて
is described by the apostle John
使徒ヨハネはヨハネ第三 4で
こう言っています
at 3 John 4, where it states:
“No greater joy do I have than this:
「私の子供たちが真理に従って
歩み続けているのを聞くことほど
“that I should hear that my children
go on walking in the truth.”
うれしいことはありません」
Yes, John is speaking
of his spiritual children.
ヨハネは真理を伝えた人たちの
ことについて言っていました
私たちも同じ喜びを味わえます
That same joy can be ours.
What has this symposium
brought to our attention?
このシンポジウムでは
どんなことを学べたでしょうか
It has helped us to see how we can maintain
熱意を冷まさないようにするには
どうしたらよいかを考えました
our zeal for the preaching work.
It has instructed us to prepare well
真理を伝えるため よく準備する
必要があることも学びました
to share the truth with others.
It showed us how to take the initiative
どうすればさまざまな機会に
自分から話し掛けられるか
to give an informal witness,
興味を示した人を助けられるか
to follow up on interest,
and to help Bible students
学んでいる人の成長を
助けられるかも学びました
grow to maturity.
If we do the best we can in the ministry,
宣教でベストを尽くすなら
たとえ人々が聞いてくれなくても
whether people respond or not,
we will enjoy the peace
that comes from knowing
平和な気持ちを持つことができます
エホバに喜ばれることを
行っているからです
that we are pleasing Jehovah.
Hebrews 13:15, 16
ヘブライ 13:15, 16には
tells us how to bring pleasure
to Jehovah God,
どうすればエホバに喜んで
いただけるかが書かれています
and that’s certainly something we want to do.
ご一緒に読んでみましょう
That’s Hebrews 13:15, 16; it reads:
ヘブライ 13:15, 16
“Through him [that is, through Jesus]
こうあります 「イエスを通して
“let us always offer to God
a sacrifice of praise,
絶えず神に賛美の犠牲を捧げましょう
神の名を人々に伝えて
“that is, the fruit of our lips
“that make public declaration to his name.
言葉で神を賛美するのです
“Moreover, do not forget to do good
さらに 善を行うことや
持っている物を分け合うことを
忘れてはなりません
“and to share what you have with others,
for God is well-pleased
with such sacrifices.”
神はそのような犠牲を
とても喜んでくださいます」
Your readiness to share
“the good news of peace” with others
「平和の良い知らせ」を
伝えている皆さんは
まさにそのような犠牲を捧げています
is just such a sacrifice.
And you can rest assured
忘れないでください
あなたが愛を込めて忠実に奉仕するなら
that Jehovah is thoroughly pleased
with your loving and faithful service to him.
エホバは心から喜んでくださるのです
ありがとうございました
Thank you, brothers,
for helping us to be ready
あらゆる機会に「平和の良い知らせ」を
上手に伝えられるよう
to share “the good news of peace” effectively
at every opportunity.
教えていただきました
Jehovah’s organization continues to grow,
エホバの組織は拡大を続けていて
and there is plenty of work to do.
たくさんの仕事があります
特に若い皆さんには さまざまな
奉仕の機会が開かれています
Young people in particular
have many opportunities
to expand their service.
How can a career in full-time service
全時間奉仕は今と将来の
祝福につながります
lead to rich blessings now and in the future?
どのようにですか
What are some common obstacles
to pursuing full-time service,
全時間奉仕をするのに
どんなことが妨げになりますか
and how can they be overcome?
どうすれば乗り越えられますか
We encourage young ones
若い皆さんはぜひ
次の話をよく聞いてください
to give special attention to the next talk.
Brother Mark Sanderson,
a member of the Governing Body,
統治体のマーク・サンダーソン兄弟が
次の主題で話してくださいます
will develop the theme
“Young People
—Choose a Path That Leads to Peace!”
「若い皆さん 平和につながる
進路を選んでください」
An 18-year-old brother
ある18歳の兄弟が
was trying to decide
what he wanted to do after high school.
高校を卒業した後
どうするかを考えていました
He was raised in the truth, and in his heart,
クリスチャンとして育てられ
心の中では開拓者に
なりたいと思っていました
he wanted to be a pioneer.
でも 大学に行くための奨学金や
But he also had a scholarship
to go to university
他の人からの援助を
受けられることになっていて
and some other grants,
and he had been accepted to attend.
受験に合格していました
He had many questions
(how was he going to support himself?)
どうやって生計を立てたらいいかなど
いろいろ悩みもありました
and much pressure from his teachers
また 大学に行くようにと 学校の
先生たちから圧力をかけられました
and counselors to go to university.
What decision would he make?
兄弟はどうするでしょうか
Well, maybe many of you young ones
who are listening to this talk right now
この話を聞いている若い皆さんも
高校を卒業したらどうしようかと
考えているかもしれません
are facing that same decision,
or maybe you will be in a year or two.
1,2年後に考える方もいるでしょう
What path will you take?
あなたはどうしたいと思いますか
Well, now, here’s what we know:
覚えておきたいことがあります
Jehovah wants you to have,
not just a good life,
エホバがあなたに望んでいるのは
それなりの人生とか
そこそこの人生ではありません
not just an average life,
素晴らしい人生を
送ってほしいと思っています
but he wants you to have an awesome,
wonderful life
—both now during your youth
若い時だけではなくて
ずっと幸せに暮らしてほしいと
思っているのです
and really for your entire life.
That’s why the Bible says
それで 伝道の書 11:9には
こう述べられています
at Ecclesiastes 11:9:
読んでみましょう
「若い人たち 若いうちに喜びなさい
“Rejoice, young man, while you are young,
and let your heart be glad
in the days of your youth.”
若い間にあなたの心が
喜びで満ちていてほしい」
多くの若い人は どのようにして
Well, many young people
have found real joy and peace
喜びや平和を味わってきたでしょうか
by choosing a career
in the full-time service.
全時間奉仕を主な
仕事とすることによってです
では 全時間奉仕とは
どういうものなのでしょうか
But now, when we say full-time service,
what are we talking about?
Well, full-time service
is not just one thing.
全時間奉仕は1種類ではありません
いろいろな奉仕が含まれています
It actually includes many things.
例えば 開拓奉仕を自分の会衆の区域や
It includes pioneering,
maybe in your home congregation
別の場所で行えるかもしれません
or maybe in another area
違う町や地方 または外国で
奉仕できるかもしれません
or maybe in another city, state,
province or even in another country.
It might mean assisting
with theocratic construction projects,
全時間奉仕には さらに
建設奉仕も含まれています
maybe building Kingdom Halls
or Assembly Halls
王国会館や大会ホールを建てたり
or building remote translation offices
遠隔翻訳事務所を建てたり
or even working at building
at Bethel facilities.
ベテルの施設を建てたり
できるかもしれません
And it also could mean
submitting an application
また ベテル奉仕の申し込みを出して
ベテル奉仕者になることも
全時間奉仕です
for Bethel service and becoming a Bethelite.
Really, there are
このように 全時間奉仕には
so many wonderful opportunities
本当にいろいろなものが含まれています
that are available for you young ones
若い皆さんにはたくさんの素晴らしい
機会が開かれています
in full-time service.
では考えてみましょう
But now, here’s a question:
あなたが全時間奉仕を始める上で
What challenges could prevent you
from starting or continuing
あるいは続けていく上で
どんなことが妨げになる
可能性があるでしょうか
on the path of full-time service?
And more important,
さらに大事なこととして
how can you overcome those challenges?
どうすればそうした問題を
乗り越えられるでしょうか
Well, let’s talk about three obstacles.
問題になりそうなことを
3つ取り上げたいと思います
Here’s the first one:
It’s financial concerns.
1つ目です
経済的な心配です
どうやって生計を
立てたらいいでしょうか
How am I going to support myself?
Well, let’s look at something that Jesus said
イエスの言葉に注目しましょう
at Matthew chapter 6
マタイ 6章の33節です
and verse 33
—Matthew 6:33.
マタイ 6:33
Jesus said: “Keep on, then,
seeking first the Kingdom
「ですから 王国と神から見て
正しいこととをいつも第一にしなさい
“and his righteousness,
そうすれば こうしたほかのもの全ても
あなたたちに与えられます」
and all these other things
will be added to you.”
Well, now, OK.
どういうことでしょう
It says “all these other things.”
「こうしたほかのもの全て」
とは何のことでしょうか
What other things?
イエスは何を言っていたのでしょう
What is Jesus talking about here?
Well, to find out,
why don’t we go back up to verse 25?
答えを知るために
25節を見てみましょう
And let’s read a little bit more
of what Jesus
ここを読むと イエスが33節で
何のことを話していたのかが分かります
was talking about when he said
those famous words
—verse 25:
25節 「それで 何を食べ何を
飲むのだろうかと自分の命のことで
“On this account I say to you:
“Stop being anxious about your lives
また何を着るのだろうかと
自分の体のことで
“as to what you will eat
or what you will drink,
“or about your bodies
as to what you will wear.
心配するのをやめなさい
“Does not life mean more than food
命は食物より 体は服より
大切ではありませんか」
and the body than clothing?”
Now (after identifying)—
ここでイエスが生活に必要なものに
ついて話していたことが分かりますね
Now, we know what Jesus is talking about:
He’s talking about our necessities
食べ物や 住む所や 服のことです
—food, shelter, clothing.
But now, look at the illustrations
Jesus goes on to give now,
では次に イエスが26節から
述べている例えに注目しましょう
beginning here in verse 26:
“Observe intently the birds of heaven;
「鳥をよく観察しなさい
“they do not sow seed or reap
or gather into storehouses,
種をまいたり 刈り取ったり
倉に集めたりはしません
それでも天の父は鳥を養っています
“yet your heavenly Father feeds them.
あなたたちはそれよりも価値が
あるのではありませんか
“Are you not worth more than they are?
心配したからといって 誰が自分の
寿命を少しでも延ばせるでしょうか
“Who of you by being anxious
can add one cubit to his life span?
“Also, why are you anxious about clothing?
また 服のことでなぜ
心配しているのですか
“Take a lesson from the lilies of the field,
野のユリがどのように
育つかをよく考えなさい
“how they grow;
they do not toil, nor do they spin;
苦労して働いたり
糸を紡いだりはしません
“but I tell you that not even Solomon
しかし ⋯⋯ソロモン王でさえ
このような花の1つほどにも
装ってはいませんでした
“in all his glory was arrayed
as one of these.
“Now if this is how God clothes
the vegetation of the field
では 神が 今日ここに生えていて
明日火に投げ込まれる野の草木に
“that is here today and tomorrow
is thrown into the oven,
このように服を与えているなら
ましてあなたたちには服を与えて
くださるのではないでしょうか
“will he not much rather clothe you,
信仰の少ない人たち
“you with little faith?
“So never be anxious and say,
‘What are we to eat?’
それで 心配して
『何を食べるのか』⋯⋯
『何を着るのか』などと
言ってはなりません
“or, ‘What are we to drink?’
or, ‘What are we to wear?’
これら全ては異国の人々が
必死に求めているものです
“For all these are the things
the nations are eagerly pursuing.
“Your heavenly Father knows
天の父は あなたたちが
こうしたもの全てを
that you need all these things.”
必要としていることを知っています」
Well, do you get the sense of this?
では 何が分かるでしょうか
エホバはご自分の創造物全てに
必要なものを与えているのですから
Jesus was trying to reason
that just as Jehovah provides
for all of his creation,
あなたにも必要なものを
与えてくれる ということです
he can provide for you too.
私たちが生活の中で神への
奉仕を第一にするなら
We just need to develop our faith
that Jehovah will provide the things we need
エホバが必ず必要なものを与えて
くれる という信仰を強めましょう
if we put his service first.
Well, does that mean
that Jehovah is just going to drop
でも エホバは必要なものを何でも
自動的に与えてくれるのでしょうか
into our lap everything that we need?
そうではありません
エホバは 私たちが
Well, no.
Jehovah expects
that we’re going to use the things
与えられた能力などを使って
that he’s given us
to be able to support ourselves.
自分で生計を立てることを
期待しています
So it’s very wise when you’re young
ですから 若いうちに将来の計画を
立てておくのは賢明です
to plan ahead so that you can obtain
自活するために必要な技術などを
the skills you need
to be able to support yourself.
前もって身に付けておくことができます
Now, in some lands,
国によっては 成長していく過程で
it may be that as you’re growing up,
お父さんやお母さんや
ほかの親戚などから
you can learn a trade from your father
仕事を教えてもらうことが
できるかもしれません
or from your mother
or maybe even from another relative.
In other lands, you might be able
while you’re still in high school
ほかの国では 高校にいる間に
職業訓練課程を
受けられるかもしれません
to take some vocational courses
仕事に役立つ技術や資格を
身に付けることができます
that would help you to learn
a skill or learn a trade.
But here’s the point: We need to plan.
いずれにしても 大事なのは
計画を立てることです
So ask yourself, ‘What abilities and skills
よく考えましょう
自活できるように どんな技術や
資格を身に付けておくといいでしょうか
do I have that I could use
to support myself?’
A sister named Kelly
ケリーという姉妹は 開拓者になる
という目標を持っていました
had a very clear goal in mind
of becoming a pioneer.
ではどうしたでしょうか
姉妹はこう言っています
So, what did she do?
Well, this is what she says:
“I had to choose something
「自活しながら宣教を行える仕事を
選ぶ必要がありました」
that would allow me
to support myself in my ministry.”
Kelly enrolled in a vocational program
in her high school,
ケリーは高校で職業訓練課程を
受けました
and that helped her
to achieve her primary goal.
それが 開拓者になるという
目標の達成に役立ちました
Here’s what she said:
“The full-time ministry
was what I wanted to do.
「私がしたかったのは全時間宣教で
ほかのものは全部二の次でした」
と言っています
Everything else was secondary.”
Well, how does Kelly feel now
about the decision that she made?
ケリーは自分の決定について
どう思っているでしょうか
「最善の決定ができたと
思います」と言って
She says: “I feel my decision
was the best one that I could have made.”
今も奉仕を楽しんでいます
You young brothers and sisters,
若い皆さんも同じように
不安を乗り越えられます
you can overcome that challenge
just by planning ahead
ぜひ良い計画を立てて
and making sure
that you have practical skills
役立つ技術や資格を身に付けるようにし
you can use to support yourself.
自活できるようにしましょう
Here’s the second obstacle:
pressure from others.
2つ目の問題です
周りからの圧力です
例えば 「稼げる仕事に
就きなさい」と言われます
‘My relatives want me
to focus on making money.’
どうしたらいいでしょうか
Well, if that’s the case,
クリスチャンとしてどんな
目標を持っているかを
explain your spiritual goals
穏やかに説明するようにしましょう
in a calm, respectful way.
Colossians 4:6 says:
コロサイ 4:6には
「塩で味付けされた快い言葉を
語るように心掛けましょう」とあります
“Let your words always be gracious,
seasoned with salt.”
Well, we all know
when we eat food with no salt,
何の味付けもされていない料理を
食べると あまりおいしくないですね
it doesn’t taste very good, does it?
でも ちょっと塩を振り掛けるだけで
We put a little salt on it
—now it becomes delicious.
たちまちとても美味しくなります
So make sure that when you
speak to your relatives,
では 自分の気持ちを説明する時にも
言葉に塩を振り掛けましょう
you put a little salt on those words
よく言葉を選んで
自分の決定が良いものだと
so that you can reason with them
and help them to see the wisdom
相手に納得して
もらえるようにしましょう
of the decision that you want to make.
Well, it could be
that your relatives will not agree with you.
それでも 相手が同意して
くれないこともあるでしょう
では イエスがルカ 7章で
何と言っているかを見てみましょう
But let’s look at something that Jesus said
here at Luke 7:35.
35節です
イエスはこう言いました
Jesus said: “All the same,
“wisdom is proved righteous
「しかし 知恵は結果によって
明らかになります」
“[or, now, if you look at the footnote,
it says, ‘or “is vindicated”’]
脚注によると 「知恵の正しさは
その全ての子供によって
by all its children.”
証明されます」となります
どういうことでしょうか
Well, now, what’s the point?
Well, sometimes when people make a decision,
誰かが何かを決定した時に
本当に正しい決定なのかどうか
分からないことがあります
we’re not sure if it
was the right one or not.
But when the decision works out well,
でも その決定が良い結果に
なったとしたらどうでしょうか
when it leads to success,
when people see how happy you are
あなたの決定の結果 あなたが幸せで
and how successful you are
—the joy, the satisfaction you have—
充実した毎日を過ごしていたら
どうでしょうか
well, then, what happens?
周りはどう思うでしょう
Well, maybe your relatives will see
きっと あなたの決定の正しさが
証明されたと思ってくれるでしょう
that your decision has been vindicated.
It’s been “proved righteous”
by the way things have turned out.
「結果によって」 良い決定だった
ことが明らかになったからです
では 3つ目の問題です
Here’s obstacle number three:
unexpected challenges.
想定外の事態です
‘I thought it was going
to be easier than this.’
思ったより大変 ということがあります
Well, those unexpected challenges
can be many.
何かと思い通りにはいかないものですね
It could be just trying
to get used to new roommates,
例えば 新しいルームメートの
言動が気になったり
気が合わなかったりするかもしれません
dealing with personality challenges,
or even just coping with homesickness.
ホームシックになることもあります
大切なのは 諦めないということです
Here’s the point: Don’t give up!
Notice what James said here
ヤコブ 1章にどんなことが書かれて
いるかに注目しましょう
in James chapter 1
—James chapter 1
ヤコブ 1章の4節です
and verse 4.
少し前の2節を見ると分かるように
Now, you notice as you look at verse 2,
ヤコブは試練について述べています
James is talking about trials,
and he’s talking about how trials
can have a positive effect on us.
試練がどのように私たちのために
なるかを論じていて
4節でこう述べています
But now look what he says in verse 4:
「忍耐するのをやめないでください
“But let endurance complete its work,
忍耐がその役割を果たす時
皆さんは完全になり
“so that you may be complete
and sound in all respects,
全ての点で健全な 欠けたところが
ない人になります」
not lacking in anything.”
What’s James trying to say?
ヤコブは何を教えたいのでしょうか
What’s his point?
Well, have you ever heard the expression
「成長には痛みが伴う」という
言葉を聞いたことがあるでしょう
“No pain, no gain”?
Well, if you want to reach
a certain fitness goal
例えば 体重を落としたい場合とか
or if you want to be very good
at playing a certain sport,
何かのスポーツでうまくなりたい場合
no doubt you’re going to have
some aching muscles.
きっと運動して筋肉痛になるでしょう
And no doubt you’re going to have
some hurt pride along the way too.
心が折れそうになるという
痛みもあるかもしれません
なかなかうまくいかない
場合があるからです
Maybe you won’t be very good
when you first start.
ではどうしますか
But what do you do?
If you want to become good,
目標を達成したいと強く
願っているなら 諦めません
if you want to reach your goal,
you can’t give up.
You have to keep trying.
努力をし続けます
クリスチャンとしての目標を達成する
ことについても 同じことが言えます
Well, the same could be said
about reaching our spiritual goals.
ヤコブの言葉によると
You see, James mentions
試練に遭った時に自分の弱さが
浮き彫りになることがあります
that trials often reveal our weaknesses.
Maybe it’s some aspect of our personality
that needs improvement.
人格を磨く必要があるかもしれません
あるいは エホバとの絆が十分に
強くないことに気付くかもしれません
Or maybe it’s something
in our relationship with Jehovah.
エホバへの信仰や信頼が
まだ足りないかもしれません
Maybe we need greater faith;
maybe we need greater trust.
そのような試練に遭った時にも
忍耐しましょう
If we endure even during periods of trial
決して諦めてはなりません
and when we refuse to give up,
we become stronger.
そうすれば強くなれます
We become stronger in our spirituality
エホバへの信仰が強くなります
and our relationship with Jehovah
エホバとの絆も強くなり
—our love for him,
our faith in him, our trust in him
エホバを一層愛するようになり
エホバへの信頼もますます深まります
just continues to grow.
ヤコブ 1:4にある通り
As James says there in verse 4,
we become “complete
and sound in all respects,
「完全になり 全ての点で健全な
欠けたところがない人」に
なることができます
not lacking in anything.”
So when those trials come
では 想定外の試練が生じたとしても
—and they will come—
すぐに全時間奉仕をやめないでください
don’t look for a quick way out.
Endure, keep going, don’t give up!
ぜひ諦めないで忍耐してください
Seek advice from brothers and sisters
who have successfully coped
同じような問題を乗り越えてきた
兄弟姉妹がいますから
アドバイスを求めましょう
with similar challenges,
and you too will be successful.
そうすれば きっとうまくいきます
In the following video,
次のビデオの中で
3人の全時間奉仕者が
notice how some full-time servants
have found real peace
これまで考えてきた
3つの問題に取り組んでいます
despite those three obstacles:
financial concerns,
経済的な心配 周りからの圧力
pressure from others,
and unexpected challenges.
想定外の事態です
I prayed to Jehovah,
「ご意志でしたら 開拓奉仕が
したいです」とエホバに祈りました
“If it is your will, I would be happy
to enter pioneer service.”
But I had to work really hard
to provide for the needs of my family
でも 家族のために
働かなければなりませんでした
because my father had died
when he was 45 years old.
父が45歳の若さで
亡くなっていたからです
The elder that I talked to
長老に相談したら
gave me advice not to be picky
about what kind of job I could get.
「仕事を選び過ぎないようにね
マタイ 6:33にあるように
He reminded me of Matthew 6:33,
and told me
心配し過ぎたらいけないよ」
と言われました
not to be overly anxious.
家族でよく話し合ううちに
Because of our good communication
within the family,
どうしたらよいかが見えてきました
we were able to find solutions.
My other siblings realized
that they also shared
一人で責任を負うのではなく
家族みんなで助け合おう
ということになったのです
responsibility in providing
for the needs of the family.
After one year of pioneering,
I was encouraged to apply for Bethel service,
開拓奉仕を1年して
ベテル奉仕を申し込むよう勧められ
and now I am in Bethel.
今ベテルにいます
I feel that Jehovah really cares for me,
loves me,
エホバは私を愛し 気に掛け
and appreciates all my efforts.
ずっと応援してくれています
いとこたちは私のためを思って
Because they love me, my cousins
pressured me to choose a secular career.
進路についてプレッシャーを
かけてきました
違う道を選んだらがっかりさせ
If I went against
their wishes, it would hurt them
関係も壊れるのではないかと
and put a strain on our relationship.
とても心配になりました
I was really anxious.
エホバに頼って 開拓奉仕がしたい
I wanted to show my trust
in Jehovah by pioneering
喜んで奉仕する姿を見てもらいたい
と思っていました
and give him an opportunity to show me
that I can be happy in his service.
いとこたちには言葉と行動で
感謝を表すようにしました
I tried to express my appreciation
for my cousins by what
I said and did
いとこたちを大切に思っている
ことも伝えました
and showed them love.
私が人として成長したと
思ってもらえたようです
They’ve realized
that I have changed for the better.
I show more concern for others now.
もっと人のために
動けるようになりました
Now they understand that we have been
learning good things and that we have
私のしていることを
認めてくれるようになりました
明るくなった 楽しそうだね
と言ってくれています
a happier and more meaningful life.
I wanted to try serving
必要の大きな所に
行きたいと思っていました
where the need was greater.
When I first arrived,
ここに来たばかりの頃
期待で胸がいっぱいでした
I thought it was so cool being there.
I had expected the poverty,
but when I saw it,
貧しい所だと分かってはいましたが
思っていた以上でした
it hit home more than what I had expected.
それでホームシックに
なってしまいました
So then I started to feel really homesick.
But my brothers and sisters—
でも集会で会う地元の兄弟姉妹は
I’d go to the Kingdom Hall and they
were able to cope with the challenges
大変な中でも エホバがいるから
大丈夫と言っていました
that they were facing because they had
Jehovah in their life.
So their example really helped me to see
that my circumstances
その様子を見て
状況がどうかということより
自分の見方次第なんだと
いうことに気が付きました
don’t need to change
for my attitude to change.
格言 15:15の言葉が
心に響きました
Proverbs 15:15 stood out to me,
which is about having “a cheerful heart”
「陽気な心」があれば
大変なことがあっても
and being able to have “a continual feast”
no matter what my circumstances are.
「毎日が宴会」だとあります
And I found an article about that scripture.
その聖句についての
記事も調べてみました
記事を読んで こう考えました
And so from there, I decided to ask myself,
‘How can I use my situation
「今の状況を生かしてほかの人のために
何ができるだろう」
and what I’m learning to help others?’
And I got to start helping
with a foreign-language group there.
外国語グループでの奉仕を始めました
That whole experience
この経験のおかげで 人を助けたい
という思いがもっと強くなりました
just made my love for people grow so much
and definitely changed my life.
自分も変われたと思います
エホバの証人ではない親族などから
Some of your non-Witness family members
might offer you secular or financial advice.
お金を稼げるいい仕事に就くよう
言われるかもしれません
あなたのためを思って
We know they mean well
幸せになってほしいという気持ちから
そのように言うのでしょう
and they feel that they’re giving you
the best advice
because they love you.
でも 若い兄弟姉妹の皆さん
But, young brothers and sisters,
ぜひ全時間奉仕を目標にすることを
お勧めしたいと思います
we are convinced that the blessings
of full-time service
ほかのどんな生き方よりもはるかに
素晴らしい祝福を味わえるからです
far outweigh any challenges
that might go along with it.
ビデオに出てきた兄弟姉妹の
経験を思い起こしてみましょう
Just think of the experiences
that we heard in the video.
Harley’s choices allowed him to go to Bethel
ハーリーは 良い選択をして
ベテルに行きました
and helped him to feel
that Jehovah really loved him.
エホバに本当に愛されていることを
実感しています
Anjil’s choices took courage,
アンジールは 勇気を出して
開拓奉仕を始め
but those choices helped him
to be more concerned about other people
前よりも人のことを
気遣えるようになりました
and helped his relatives to see
いとこたちも 良い生き方を
していると認めてくれました
that he had made a good decision.
And Carlee did not give up
when the trials came.
カーリーは 試練に遭っても
諦めませんでした
その結果 人を助けたいという
思いがもっと強くなって
Instead, she learned
to love other people even more
and became a more powerful, strong Christian.
強い信仰を持つクリスチャンとして
成長することができました
若い皆さん 私たちは
Brothers and sisters, why are we so convinced
全時間奉仕が素晴らしい人生に
つながると確信しています
that full-time service
will lead you young ones
to a wonderful life?
どうしてでしょうか
Well, it’s because that’s the decision
私たちの多くも 若い時から
全時間奉仕をしているからです
that so many of us made when we were young.
Do you remember
that 18-year-old young brother
この話の冒頭でどうするか悩んでいた
who was trying to decide which path to take?
18歳の兄弟を覚えていますか
Well, that was me some years ago.
実は あれは若い時の私です
I’m so glad
うれしいことに 私はエホバや両親や
that with the help of Jehovah and my parents
会衆内の円熟した
友人たちに助けてもらって
and other mature friends in the congregation,
良い決定ができました
I made the decision
世界中にいる非常に大勢の
兄弟姉妹たちと同じように
just like so many other brothers
and sisters around the world
奨学金を辞退して
to turn down that scholarship,
大学に進学しないことにしました
to give up university,
and to go directly
into the full-time service.
そして すぐに全時間奉仕を始めました
That is a decision
that I have never regretted;
その決定を後悔したことは
一度もありません
that is a decision that I will never regret.
そして今後も 後悔することは
絶対にないでしょう
若い皆さん エホバは
皆さんを愛しています
Young people, Jehovah loves you.
He wants you to have
a wonderful, awesome life.
素晴らしい人生を
送ってほしいと思っています
Choose the path
of full-time service if you can.
できることなら
全時間奉仕をしてください
決して後悔はしません
You will never regret it.
その進路は 確かに平和につながります
It will put you on a path
that leads to joy and peace
素晴らしい神エホバに仕えて
with our marvelous, wonderful God, Jehovah.
いつまでも続く喜びを味わえるのです
Thank you, Brother Sanderson,
サンダーソン兄弟
若い時に全時間奉仕をするよう
for the warm encouragement
to pursue full-time service
温かく励ましてくださり
ありがとうございました
from an early age.
ではご一緒に135番
「エホバの温かな呼び掛け
Now we invite all to join
in singing song number 135,
“Jehovah’s Warm Appeal: ‘Be Wise, My Son.’”
『わが子よ 賢く』ありなさい」という
歌を歌いましょう
That’s song number 135.
135番の歌です